Connecticut School Desegregation Collection 2002.0044
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
Connecticut School Desegregation Collection
1965-1994.
2002.0044
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
3.55 Linear feet
The Connecticut School Desegregation Collection consisits of materials related to the legal issues surrounding school desegregation in Hartford and Bridgeport, Connecticut. The collection provides an overview of the regional and national concerns in the area of desegregation, and two court cases that fought to bring an end to school segregation and discrimination.
Koskoff, Koskoff & Bieder, PC.
Tirozzi, Gerald.
History
The issue of desegregation of Connecticut's schools became a legal one in 1975 and continues today. The collection provides an overview of regional and national concerns in the area of desegregation.
In 1989 Milo Sheff, a ten year old fourth grader from Hartford, CT, joined with seventeen other school children to file a lawsuit against the state of Connecticut, and Governor William O'Neill. Alledging that their constitutional rights to a public education and their rights to equal protection under the law were being violated, they called for the state to change its existing policy on educational equality. The case was originally argued in Hartford Superior Court, and was ruled in favor of the state and the governor. The judge ruled that school officials were not obligated to correct educational inequalities, no matter how they may have come to transpire. Following the finding by the Superior Court, the case was appealed to the Connecticut Supreme Court. In 1996 the superior court overruled the lower court's ruling, stating that the state did in fact have an obligation to provide Connecticut's school children with equal educational opportunities. It also ruled that children had a constitutional right to a public education, one that could not be altered based on ethnic or racial background.
The debate surrounding Bridgeport's public school desegregation began in the 1970s and continued throughout the 1980s. In November 1975 the NAACP, the Spanish American Coalition (SAC), a group of community organizations, and individual black and hispanic parents filed a lawsuit in U.S. District Court against the Bridgeport Board of Education, and the Connecticut State Board of Education. In 1978 the Mayor, Comptroller, and Board of Appointment and Taxation were added as defendants. The lawsuit was filed because the plaintiffs believed the Board of Education had created a dual school system, discriminating against black and hispanic students.
Scope and Content
The collection contains legal files, documents, reports, studies, correspondence, publications, conference proceedings, papers and similar materials pertaining to two lawsuits concerning the desegregation of Connecticut's public schools.
Series I contains materials related to Connecticut's Sheff v. O'Neill case, 1965-1994, and contains documents issued by state agencies, educational associations and the city of Hartford, as well as reports from academic institutions. Also included is a comprehensive, annotated bibliography of the documents compiled by David R. Gilmore. The exhibits have been arranged chronologically and assigned a file number, which is cross-referenced in the bibliography.
Series II is comprised of the Bridgeport School Desegregation Files (undated, 1972-1983). The series contains publications, papers and conference proceedings collected in connection with the desegregation of the Bridgeport public schools. Also included in the series are reference materials related to school desegregation cases in other American cities. The type of materials in the series are similar in nature to those in Series I and therefore have also been arranged chronologically by publication date.
Arrangement
Series I: Sheff v. O'Neill ( 1965-1994 ) contains documents issued by state agencies, educational associations and the city of Hartford, as well as reports from academic institutions. Also included is a comprehensive, annotated bibliography of the documents compiled by David R. Gilmore. The exhibits have been arranged chronologically and assigned a file number, which is cross-referenced in the bibliography.
Series II: Bridgeport School Desegregation Files ( undated, 1972-1983 ) contains publications, papers and conference proceedings collected in connection with the desegregation of the Bridgeport public schools. The materials are similar in nature to those in Series I and therefore have also been arranged chronologically by publication date.
Acquisition Information
The Sheff v. O'Neill materials were donated in 1996, presumably by Mr. Tirozzi (no documentation). The Bridgeport materials were donated in 2001 by the law firm of Koskoff, Koskoff & Bieder.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to various aspects of Connecticut history. See especially the Connecticut Civil Liberties Union Records. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the Reading Room desk.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Correspondence.; Discrimination in education--Connecticut.; Educational law and legislation--Connecticut.; Legal Records.; Minorities--Education--Connecticut--Hartford.; Publications.; School integration--Connecticut--Bridgeport.; School integration--Connecticut--Hartford.; Segregation in education--Connecticut.; Sheff, Milo Trials, litigation, etc.; Unknown.
- Series I: Sheff v. O'Neill, 1965-1994
  - Bibliography [see also Appendix A], undated (Box 1:, Folder 1)
  - Exhibits [numbers correspond to bibliography]
    - 1— Schools for Hartford, 1965 (Box 1:, Folder 2)
    - 2— Summary of Harvard Report, 1965 (Box 1:, Folder 3)
    - 3— Proposal to Plan and Study School Programs from Children Involved in a Regional Desegregation Plan, 1966 (Box 1:, Folder 4)
    - 4— Equality and Quality in the Public Schools: Report of a Conference, 1966 (Box 1:, Folder 5)
    - 5— Equality of Education Opportunity, 1966 (Box 1:, Folder 6)
    - 6— Policy Statement Concerning Quality of Education for Children in Minority Groups, 1966 (Box 1:, Folder 7)
    - 7— Policy Statement Concerning Quality of Education for Children in Minority Groups, 1967 (Box 1:, Folder 8)
    - 8— Correspondence from Mr. Steel to Commissioner Sanders; Statement of Policy Proposed for adoption by representatives of NAACP to CT State Board of Education; Statement of Policy on De Facto Segregated Public Schools from Board of Regents, SUNY; Correspondence from NY Commissioner Allen to Local Educational Agencies, 1967 (Box 1:, Folder 9)
    - 9— Minority Imbalance in Connecticut Schools, ca. 1967 (Box 1:, Folder 10)
    - 10— Memo from Intergroup Education Division to Education Subcommittee, Legislative Commission on Human Rights and Opportunities regarding problem of interdistrict segregation, 1968 (Box 1:, Folder 11)
    - 11— De Facto School Segregation and the Student: A Study of the Schools in Connecticut's Five Major Cities, 1968 (Box 1:, Folder 12)
    - 12— Changes in Racial Composition and De Facto Segregation in Pupils in the Public Schools of Five Connecticut Cities: 1963-1967, 1969 (Box 1:, Folder 13)
    - 13— A Study of Urban School Needs in the Five Largest Cities in Connecticut, 1969 (Box 1:, Folder 14)
    - 14— Report of the Legislative Commission on Human Rights and opportunities, 1969 (Box 1:, Folder 15)
    - 15— Racial Imbalance and Regionalization, 1969 (Box 1:, Folder 16)
    - 16— Public Act No. 773: An Act Concerning Racial Imbalance in the Public Schools, 1969 (Box 1:, Folder 17)
    - 17— Preliminary Report on the Distribution of Minority-Group Pupils in Connecticut Public Schools, 1968-1969, ca. 1969 (Box 1:, Folder 18)
    - 18— Complaint in Lumpkin v. Dempsey, 1970 (Box 1:, Folder 19)
    - 19— Community Development Action Plan: Education 1971-1975, 1970 (Box 1:, Folder 20)
    - 20— Complaint in Hartford v. Meskill, 1972 (Box 1:, Folder 21)
    - 21— Memorandum Summarizing Plaintiff's Proof in Lumpkin v. Meskill, 1972 (Box 1:, Folder 22)
    - 22— Financing Connecticut's Schools: Final Report of the Commission to Study School Finance and Equal Educational Opportunity, 1975 (Box 1:, Folder 23)
    - 23— A Plan for Promoting Equal Educational Opportunity in Connecticut, 1979 (Box 2:, Folder 24)
    - 24— Advancing Equal Education Opportunity and Access to Quality Integrated Education in the Public Schools of the State of CT, ca. 1980 (Box 2:, Folder 25)
    - 25— Advisory Report: Policy and Planning Implications, 1981 (Box 2:, Folder 26)
    - 26— A Plan for Compliance with the Racial Imbalance Regulations of the Connecticut State Department of Education, 1981 (Box 2:, Folder 27)
    - 27— Vocational Guidance Quarterly, 31, pp. 230-239, 1983 (Box 2:, Folder 28)
    - 28— Connecticut's Challenge: An Agenda for Educational Equity and Excellence, 1984 (Box 2:, Folder 29)
    - 29— A Report Providing Background Information Concerning the Chronology and Status of Statutes, Regulations, and Processes Regarding Racial Imbalance in CT Schools, 1984 (Box 2:, Folder 30)
    - 30— Interim Report of the Racial Imbalance Law and Regulations Advisory Committee, 1985 (Box 2:, Folder 31)
    - 31— Strategic Plan to Ensure Racial and Ethnic Diversity in Connecticut Public Higher Education, 1985 (Box 2:, Folder 32)
    - 32— School Desegregation and Black Occupational Attainments: Results from a Long-term Experiment, 1985 (Box 2:, Folder 33)
    - 33— The Issue of Racial Imbalance and Quality Education in Connecticut's Public Schools, 1986 (Box 2:, Folder 34)
    - 34— Circular Letter C-15 on the State Board of Education Policy Statement on Equal Educational Opportunity, 1986 (Box 2:, Folder 35)
    - 35— Metropolitan Education, 1, pp. 65-77, 1986 (Box 2:, Folder 36)
    - 36— Connecticut's Common Core of Learning, 1987 (Box 2:, Folder 37)
    - 37— Report from the Bilingual Education Legislation Review Task Force to the Commissioner of Education, 1987 (Box 2:, Folder 38)
    - 38— Composite document containing deliberations on Racial Imbalance Act Regulations, 1969-1987 (Box 2:, Folder 39)
    - 39— Connecticut State Department of Education Report on the Recommendations Issued by the Bilingual Education Legislation Review Task Force, 1987 (Box 2:, Folder 40)
    - 40— Briefing on Existing State Programs, ca. 1987 (Box 2:, Folder 41)
    - 41— A Report on Racial/Ethnic Equity and Desegregation in Connecticut's Public Schools, 1988 (Box 2:, Folder 42)
    - 42— Alternate Proposal to Address Racial Imbalance, 1988 (Box 2:, Folder 43)
    - 43— Background and Discussion Paper on School Racial/Ethnic Balance, 1988 (Box 2:, Folder 44)
    - 44— Indicators of Success: A Report on Progress in Implementing the Goals and Objectives of “Design for Excellence: Connecticut's Comprehensive Plan for Elementary, Secondary, Vocational, Career and Adult Education, 1988 (Box 2:, Folder 45)
    - 45— Quality and Integrated Education: Options for Connecticut, 1989 (Box 3:, Folder 46)
    - 46— Cover Memo and Copy of Governor Weicker's Charge to the Commission on Quality and Integrated Education, 1989 (Box 3:, Folder 47)
    - 47— Governor's Commission on Quality and Integrated Education Request for Foundation Support: Prospectus, 1989 (Box 3:, Folder 48)
    - 48— A Pastoral Statement on School Desegregation in Connecticut, 1989 (Box 3:, Folder 49)
    - 49— Review of Research on School Desegregation's Impact on Elementary, 1989 (Box 3:, Folder 50)
    - 50— In Pursuit of Promise, 1990 (Box 3:, Folder 51)
    - 51— Challenge for Excellence” Connecticut's Comprehensive Plan for Elementary, Secondary, Vocational, Career and Adult Education: A Policy Plan 1991-1995, 1990 (Box 3:, Folder 52)
    - 52— Addendum to Background and Discussion Paper on School Racial/Ethnic Balance, 1990 (Box 3:, Folder 53)
    - 53— Interoffice Memorandum on Crossing the Bridge to Equity and Excellence: A Vision of Quality and Integrated Education for CT, 1990 (Box 3:, Folder 54)
    - 54— Chronology of State of CT Activities Advancing Racial/Ethnic Equity and Desegregation in CT's Public Schools w/ Cover Memo re State Racial Imbalance Laws, 1990 (Box 3:, Folder 55)
    - 55— Special Connecticut Mastery Test Report: Students at Risk Academically, 1990 (Box 3:, Folder 56)
    - 56— PAQIE: Inventory of Progress to Reduce Racial Imbalance, with cover memo from Joan Martin, 1990 (Box 3:, Folder 57)
    - 57— Next Steps re “Quality and Integrated Education: Options for CT, 1990 (Box 3:, Folder 58)
    - 58— Critical Components of Integration Plans, 1990 (Box 3:, Folder 59)
    - 59— Strategic Plan to Ensure Racial and Ethnic Diversity in CT Public Higher Education: The First Five Years 1985-1990 (Box 3:, Folder 60)
    - 60— Statewide Evaluation of the Priority School District Program: A Second Triennial Report, 1990 (Box 3:, Folder 61)
    - 61— Crossing the Bridge to Equality and Excellence: A Vision of Quality and Integrated Education for CT, 1990 (Box 3:, Folder 62)
    - 62— Getting to the Heart of the Matter: Key Strategies for Achieving High Quality and True Integration in CT's School: An Addendum to the Draft Report of the Governor's Commission on Quality and Integrated Education, 1990 (Box 3:, Folder 63)
    - 63— Connecticut's Education Initiative: The Vision and Reality, 1990 (Box 3:, Folder 64)
    - 64— Indicators of Success: A Report on Progress in Implementing the Goals and Objectives of “Design for Excellence: CT's Comprehensive Plan for Elementary, Secondary, Vocational, Career and Adult Education, 1986-1990 (Box 3:, Folder 65)
    - 65— Meeting the Challenge: Condition of Education in Connecticut, 1990/91, 1991 (Box 3:, Folder 66)
    - 66— Tables of Desegregation, Expenditures, Demographics, and Attitude Survey Data, Connecticut and Nationwide, 1991 (Box 3:, Folder 67)
    - 67— Final Evaluation Report: 1990-1991 Hartford Project Concern Program, with Appendix: Almost 25 years of Project Concern: An Overview of the Program and its Accomplishments (Box 3:, Folder 68)
    - 68— Proposed Integration, Desegregation and Racial Balance Bills in CT, 1981-1991 (Box 3:, Folder 69)
    - 69— A Major Proposal for the Restructuring of CT's Educational Delivery System, 1992 (Box 3:, Folder 70)
    - 70— A Proposed Three Year Design for the Project Concern Evaluation, 1992 (Box 4:, Folder 71)
    - 71— Connecticut's Limited-English-Proficient Students: A Neglected Resource, 1992 (Box 4:, Folder 72)
    - 72— Solutions for CT's Public Schools in the 1990s and Beyond, 1992 (Box 4:, Folder 73)
    - 73— The Urban Agenda, 1992 (Box 4:, Folder 74)
    - 74— Connecticut Recruitment Network for Educational Diversity: Its Forum, 1992 (Box 4:, Folder 75)
    - 75— Finding Niches: Desegregated Students Sixteen Years Later—Final Report on the Educational Outcomes of Project Concern, Hartford, Connecticut, 1992 (Box 4:, Folder 76)
    - 76— Minority Students and Staff Report, 1992 (Box 4:, Folder 77)
    - 77— Environmental Factors Influencing Educational Program Outcomes: A Review of Research, 1992 (Box 4:, Folder 78)
    - 78— State Department of Education Activities in Response to Recommendations Proposed in “Crossing the Bridge to Equality and Excellence”, 1992 (Box 4:, Folder 79)
    - 79— Total Education (Draft), 1992 (Box 4:, Folder 80)
    - 80— Cover Memo to Attys. Tegeler and Stone re Exhibit 498, 1992 (Box 4:, Folder 81)
    - 81— A Descriptive Study of the Educational Resources of the Hartford Public Schools and Disparities with other Districts, 1992 (Box 4:, Folder 82)
    - 82— Major State Policies and Programs affecting Public Education, 1992 (Box 4:, Folder 83)
    - 83— Plaintiff's Opening Argument in Sheff v. O'Neill, 1992 (Box 4:, Folder 84)
    - 84— Opening Statement by Professor John Brittain in Sheff v. O'Neill, 1992 (Box 4:, Folder 85)
    - 85— Opening Statement by Assistant Attorney General John Whelan in Sheff v. O'Neill, 1992 (Box 4:, Folder 86)
    - 86— Indicators of Success: A Report of Progress in Implementing the Goals and Objectives of “Challenge for Excellence: Connecticut's Comprehensive Plan for Elementary, Secondary, Vocational, Career and Adult Education—A Policy Plan 1991-1995”, 1992 (Box 4:, Folder 87)
    - 87— A Voice and a Choice for Connecticut: Governor Weicker Unveils Plan for Quality, Integrated Schools, 1993 (Box 4:, Folder 88)
    - 88— Memorandum to CSDE Associated Commissioners and Bureau Chiefs re Testimony of Witnesses in Sheff v. O'Neill, 1993 (Box 4:, Folder 89)
    - 89— Defendants' Post-Trial Brief in Sheff v. O'Neill, CV 89-0360977S, 1993 (Box 4:, Folder 90)
    - 90— Plaintiff's Post-Trial Brief in Sheff v. O'Neill, 1993 (Box 5:, Folder 91)
    - 91— Plaintiff's Reply Brief in Sheff v. O'Neill, 1993 (Box 5:, Folder 92)
    - 92— Public Act No. 93-263 An Act Improving Educational Quality and Diversity, 1993 (Box 5:, Folder 93)
    - 93— Guide for the Local Advisory Process under Public Act 93-263, An Act Improving Educational Quality and Diversity, 1993 (Box 5:, Folder 94)
    - 94— Report on School Desegregation Survey, 1993 (Box 5:, Folder 95)
    - 95— Request for Proposals: Interdistrict Cooperative Grant 1994-1995 (Box 5:, Folder 96)
    - 96— Request for Proposals: Interdistrict Magnet School under the Interdistrict Cooperative Grant, 1994 (Box 5:, Folder 97)
- Series II: Bridgeport School Desegregation Files, (undated, 1972-1983)
  - School Desegregation Organizers' Manual, undated (Box 6:, Folder 98)
  - Bridgeport School Desegregation—Twenty Questions and Answers, undated (Box 6:, Folder 99)
  - Your Child and Busing, 1972 (Box 6:, Folder 100)
  - It's Not the Distance, “It's the Niggers.” Comments on the Controversy over School Busing, 1972 (Box 6:, Folder 101)
  - School Desegregation in Ten Communities, 1973 (Box 6:, Folder 102)
  - Equal Opportunity in Suburbia, 1974 (Box 6:, Folder 103)
  - Continuing Challenge: The Past and Future of Brown v. Board of Education, 1975 (Box 6:, Folder 104)
  - Making Civil Rights Sense out of Revenue Sharing Dollars, 1975 (Box 6:, Folder 105)
  - Twenty Years after Brown: Equality of Educational Opportunity, 1975 (Box 6:, Folder 106)
  - Law and Contemporary Problems, v. 39, #2, 1975 (Box 6:, Folder 107)
  - Citizen Guide to Desegregation: A Report of the Citizens' Council for Ohio Schools, 1976 (Box 6:, Folder 108)
  - University of Chicago School Review, v. 84, #3, 1976 (Box 6:, Folder 109)
  - School Desegregation—Making It Work, 1976 (Box 6:, Folder 110)
  - Fulfilling the Letter and Spirit of the Law: Desegregation of the Nation's Public Schools, 1976 (Box 7:, Folder 111)
  - School Desegregation in Colorado Springs, CO, 1977 (Box 7:, Folder 112)
  - Adopt-A-School Dallas Style: A Community Participation Model, 1977 (Box 7:, Folder 113)
  - School Desegregation in Kalamazoo, MI, 1977 (Box 7:, Folder 114)
  - School Desegregation in Ogden, UT, 1977 (Box 7:, Folder 115)
  - School Desegregation in Erie, PA, 1977 (Box 7:, Folder 116)
  - School Desegregation in Minneapolis, MN, 1977 (Box 7:, Folder 117)
  - Viewpoints and Guidelines on Court Appointed Citizens Monitoring Commissions in School Desegregation, 1977 (Box 7:, Folder 118)
  - School Desegregation in Williamsburg County, SC, 1977 (Box 7:, Folder 119)
  - School Desegregation in Peoria, IL, 1977 (Box 7:, Folder 120)
  - School Desegregation in Little Rock, AR., 1977 (Box 7:, Folder 121)
  - School Desegregation in Nashville-Davidson, TN, 1977 (Box 7:, Folder 122)
  - School Desegregation in Racine, WI, 1977 (Box 7:, Folder 123)
  - School Desegregation in Kirkwood, MO, 1977 (Box 7:, Folder 124)
  - School Desegregation in Santa Barbara, CA, 1977 (Box 7:, Folder 125)
  - School Desegregation in Greenville, MS, 1977 (Box 7:, Folder 126)
  - School Desegregation in Waterloo, IA, 1977 (Box 7:, Folder 127)
  - School Desegregation in Ossining, NY, 1977 (Box 7:, Folder 128)
  - School Desegregation in Berkeley, CA, 1977 (Box 7:, Folder 129)
  - Government, Politics and the Public Schools: A Preliminary Study of Three Cities, 1977 (Box 7:, Folder 130)
  - Desegregation and Black Achievement (Working Paper), 1977 (Box 7:, Folder 131)
  - School Desegregation in Metropolitan Areas: Choices and Prospects, 1977 (Box 7:, Folder 132)
  - Urban School Desegregation Costs. Part I. Case Studies, 1977 (Box 7:, Folder 133)
  - Integrated Education, Issue #90, v. 15, #6, 1977 (Box 8:, Folder 134)
  - Evaluation of the Impact of ESEA Title VII Spanish/English Bilingual Education Program v. III, 1978 (Box 8:, Folder 135)
  - Resolving the Desegregation Issue in the St. Louis Public Schools. Part I, 1978 (Box 8:, Folder 136)
  - Citizen Guide to Quality Education: A Report of the Citizens' Council for Ohio Schools, 1978 (Box 8:, Folder 137)
  - Desegregation: Problems, Successes and Next Steps, 1978 (Box 8:, Folder 138)
  - Report and Recommendations of the Joint Select Committee on School Desegregation to the Ohio General Assembly, 1978 (Box 8:, Folder 139)
  - Resolving the Desegregation Issue in the St. Louis Public Schools. Part II, 1978 (Box 8:, Folder 140)
  - Orderly Schools that Serve All Children, 1979 (Box 8:, Folder 141)
  - Progress—A Report of Desegregation Trends in the States, 1980 (Box 8:, Folder 142)
  - Legal Analysis—Trends in School Desegregation Law #4, 1980 (Box 8:, Folder 143)
  - State Leadership Toward Desegregating Education: A Positive Future, 1980 (Box 8:, Folder 144)
  - procedural Manual for Monitoring, Dispute Resolution and Modification of Federal Desegregation Court Orders in the Boston Public Schools, 1983 (Box 8:, Folder 145)
  - APPENDIX A, PA 93-263 Evaluation Project
    - THIRTY CONNECTICUT YEARS: A Bibliography of Desegregation Activity in Connecticut, by David R. Gilmore., 1965-1944